Guide to the Florence Cane Papers MC.323
New York University Archives
Florence Cane Papers
1920-1963
New York University Archives
Cane, Florence, 1882-1952
American Art Therapy Association
MC.323
3.04 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 1 small box, 1 small flat box, 1 slide case, and 1 folder in shared flat box
Florence Cane (1882-1952) was an artist, art therapist, author, and the older sister of Margaret Naumburg known for her influential theoretical outlook on the use of art in expressive therapies. Cane's only published book, The Artist in Each of Us (1951), is regarded as one of the first art therapy texts. Cane is also credited for the development of the "scribble technique" (sometimes attributed to her sister Margaret). Cane taught in private practice at Naumburg's The Children's School (later known as the Walden School), and in 1936, became the director of art at the Counseling Center for Gifted Children of the School of Education at New York University. The Florence Cane Papers (dated 1920-1963) consist of materials created and collected by Cane documenting Cane's professional career as an early art therapist and professor at New York University. Materials in this collection include notebooks, photographs, correspondence, publications, glass slides, and stamps.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in boxes 1-4 are open without restrictions. Box 5 is restricted until 2099 because it contains photographs with personal health information (PHI). All other materials are open without restrictions. University Archives staff will review all requested material for PHI before providing access.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Cynthia Young (Woodruff) on behalf of the American Art Therapy Association Archives in April 2019. Prior custodial history of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.051.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into two series, as follows:
Series I. Teaching and Artwork
Series II. Publications
Generally, materials are arranged chronologically within each series.
Biographical Note
Florence Cane (1882-1952) was an artist, art therapist, author, and the older sister of Margaret Naumburg known for her influential theoretical outlook on the use of art in expressive therapies. Cane's only published book, The Artist in Each of Us (1951), is regarded as one of the first art therapy texts. Cane is also credited for the development of the "scribble technique" (sometimes attributed to her sister Margaret). Cane taught in private practice at Naumburg's The Children's School (later known as the Walden School), and in 1936, became the director of art at the Counseling Center for Gifted Children of the School of Education at New York University. She also founded the Florence Cane School of Art in 1934.
Scope and Contents
The Florence Cane Papers (dated 1920-1963) consist of materials created and collected by Cane documenting her professional career as an early art therapist, author, artist, and professor at New York University. Materials in this collection include photographs of students' artwork, correspondence, publications, glass slides, and stamps. The bulk of the photographs were included in her book and other published writing in peer-reviewed journals. There is some professional correspondence with publishers, teaching institutions, and individuals; topics include writing reviews for publications, job opportunities, and expressions of gratitude for the publication of her book. Additionally, there are some clippings and promotional materials for her book, school, and her own artwork. Her teaching methods and techniques are expressed not only in the photographs of her students' work, but in her syllabi and lecture notes.
Art therapy.; Art therapists; Psychotherapy.; Women authors; American Art Therapy Association
- Series I. Teaching and Artwork, 1920-1952; 2.60 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, 1 small flat box, 1 slide case, and 1 folder in a shared flat box
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of materials created and used by Cane when teaching as well as exhibition catalogues of her own artwork. These materials illustrate her philosophies and teaching methods, especially through the descriptions of the students' artwork. Materials include syllabi, lecture notes, correspondence with students and teaching institutions, photographs of artwork by students, student exhibition catalogues, glass slides (of students' artwork, including that of teachers, and her own artwork), and stamps. Also included are Cane's biography, photographs, and obituary.
  - Biography and Photographs, circa 1938-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibitions of Cane's Artwork, 1920-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lectures and Speeches, 1926-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New York University School of Education, 1929-1951
    - Clinic for Gifted Children, 1929-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 5, Folder 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Photograph in box 5, folder 1 is restricted until 2099.
    - "A Method of Teaching Creative Art", 1931-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Westchester Workshop, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Florence Cane School of Art, 1935-1937
    - Teachers' Course, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 5, Folder 2)
      Photographs in box 5, folder 2 are restricted until 2099.
    - Brochures and Publicity, 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Poster -- Cane's Philosophy on Creation, undated (Box Shared University Archives 152, Folder 12)
  - Stamps -- Models of Heads and Mouths, undated (Box 4)
  - Glass Slides of Students' Artwork, undated (Box 3, Box 6)
- Series II. Publications, 1926-1963; 1.10 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
  This series contains samples of Cane's published writing in various journals and materials used in her book. All of her writing focuses on teaching art with an emphasis on its therapeutic characteristics and the value of creativity. Materials mostly consist of final publications (most of which are periodicals) and in a few instances, drafts; promotional materials for her book; letters of commendation from readers; and correspondence with publishers. Additionally, there are photographs of artwork used in her published book.
  - Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Painting as a Channel for the Subjective Life" -- Survey Graphic, June 1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Art and the Child's Essential Nature" -- Creative Art, February 1929 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Creative Impulse in Children" -- Revival: The Next Generation -- Edited by Victor Francis Calverton and Samuel Daniel Schmalhausen, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Art and the Child's Essential Nature" -- The Villager, February 1931 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "What Art May Mean to a Child" -- The Parents' Magazine, November 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "The Gifted Child in Art" -- Journal of Educational Sociology, July-October 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1, Box 5, Folder 3)
    Photographs in box 5, folder 3 are restricted until 2099.
  - "Possibilities of Integration Through Art" -- Art Education Today, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Draft Appendix -- Creative Expression Through Art -- Progressive Education Association, circa 1942 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Draft Review of Education Through Art by Herbert Read -- The Journal of Educational Sociology, December 1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Artist in Each of Us, 1938-1963
    - Photographs Used, circa 1938-1951 (Box 2, Folder 5-7, Box 5, Folder 4)
      Photographs in box 5, folder 4 are restricted until 2099.
    - Press and Publicity, 1951-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)